Guide to the United States Political Campaign Materials Collection, 1840-2009 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United States Political Campaign Materials collection 1840-2009 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
10.8 linear feet Extent: 3033 items
Collection of campaign ephemera and other materials assembled by staff at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Collection of campaign materials spans much of the United States political timeline, from 1840 to 2009. National and state political campaigns run by the Whig, Know-Nothing, Democratic, Republican, Libertarian, and other parties are documented through printed material, artifacts, and ephemera, such as posters, flyers, buttons, bumper stickers, party platforms, pamphlets, texts of speeches, newspapers, and clippings. Materials from state campaigns and other elections such as mayoral races chiefly come from North Carolina, with smaller amounts from Louisiana, Maryland, Massachusetts, and other states. There are some materials documenting Durham, North Carolina political history, as well as a few items pertaining to a Humphrey-Muskie committee at Duke University. Other political organizations and caucuses are also represented, including anti-war organizations, labor unions (especially the AFL-CIO), and various other citizens' groups.
politicalcampaign
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The items in the United States Political Campaign Materials Collection were acquired from a variety of sources by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library and assembled over a period of time, roughly from the 1950s to 2009.
Collection Overview
Collection of campaign materials spans most of the United States political timeline, from 1840 to 2009. National and state political campaigns run by the Whig, Know-Nothing, Democratic, Republican, Libertarian, Greenback, Independent, Citizens, and other parties, are documented through printed material, artifacts, and ephemera, such as posters, flyers, buttons, bumper stickers, party platforms, texts of speeches, pamphlets, newspapers, and clippings. Many of the items related to national party conventions. Materials from state campaigns and other elections such as mayoral races chiefly come from North Carolina, with smaller amounts from Louisiana, Maryland, Massachusetts, and other states. There are some materials documenting 20th century Durham, North Carolina political history, as well as a few items pertaining to a Humphrey-Muskie Committee at Duke University. Other political organizations and caucuses are also represented, including anti-war organizations, labor unions (especially the AFL-CIO), and various other citizens' groups such as the NAACP. The collection is divided into four series: National Elections, America Votes (materials from a 1996 exhibit of campaign memorabilia at Duke), State Elections, and Political Campaign Memorabilia. Each series is arranged by election year, with a few exceptions, and within, alphabetically by party, state, or topic. There is also a group of oversize materials separated from the main collection, chiefly newspapers and posters.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
AFL-CIO -- History; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People -- History; Democratic Party (U.S.)--History; Greenback Party (U.S.)--History; American Independent Party (U.S.)--History; Citizens Party (U.S.)--History; Libertarian Party (U.S.)--History; Know-Nothing Party (U.S.)--History; Republican Party (U.S.)--History; Socialist Party (U.S.)--History; Whig Party (U.S.)--History; Elections -- United States -- History; Political conventions -- United States -- History; Labor movement -- United States -- History; Peace movements -- United States -- History; Political campaigns -- United States -- History; Political campaigns -- North Carolina -- History; Political parties -- United States -- History; Presidential candidates -- United States; Presidents -- United States -- Election; Durham (N.C.)--Politics and government; Louisiana -- Politics and government; North Carolina -- Politics and government; Maryland -- Politics and government; Massachusetts -- Politics and government; Buttons (information artifacts).; Memorabilia; Posters; Pamphlets; Bumper stickers; Clippings
Related Material
The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library holds thousands of bound pamphlets and manuscript collections relating to United States elections, as well as archival collections focused on individual political figures, particularly in the state of North Carolina, and Durham, Orange, and Wake counties. In addition, the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library holds these collections containing materials closely related to or complementing the collection described in this finding aid:
[Collection of pamphlets, containing propaganda for various presidential elections. Issued by friends and adherents of the Republican party], undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kenneth Hubbard Collection of Political Campaign Ephemera, 1880-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard Bentley Collection of Presidential Campaign Memorabilia, 1961-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard E. McDonald Political Campaign Collection, undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Socialist Party (U.S.) Records, 1900-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- National Elections Series, 1840-2009 and undated, (6 boxes)
  - 1840: (Box 1)
    - Whig Party, The Triumphant Whig Song
  - 1856:
    - Democratic Party, clippings
  - 1880:
    - Republican Party, Garfield and Arthur campaign song book
  - 1940:
    - Republican Party, Willkie, Wendell
  - 1944, 1952:
    - Socialist Party, pamphlets and convention minutes
  - 1947-1948:
    - Democratic Party
      - Publicity Division, newspaper statements
      - Speeches and other literature
  - 1948:
    - Democratic Party
      - Literature, (2 folders)
      - The Democratic Digest, July-Nov.
    - Dixiecrat Party, An Open Letter to Dixiecrats
    - Republican Party, Republican Fact Book
  - 1952:
    - Democratic Party
      - Harriman, William Averell
      - Kefauver, Estes
      - Kerr, Robert Samuel
      - Russell, Richard Brevard
      - Presidential campaign materials
      - Clippings and pamphlets
      - Stevenson, Adlai Ewing, Speeches, (folder 1 of 6)
      - Stevenson, Adlai Ewing, speeches, (folders 2-6 of 6) (Box 2)
    - Greenback Party, platform, candidates and officers
    - NAACP, Survey of the Negro Vote in the 1953 Presidential Election
    - Prohibition Party, printed material
    - Republican Party
      - Stassen, Harold Edward
      - Taft, Robert Alphonso
      - Warren, Earl
      - Pamphlets and other literature
      - Convention keynote address and other literature
      - Clippings (Box 3)
      - Eisenhower Letter, Apr. 4-July 1
      - Eisenhower, Dwight David, printed material, (2 folders)
  - 1956:
    - Democratic Party, platform and printed material
    - Republican Party
      - Election issues of 1956, (2 folders)
      - Johnson, Joel A.,correspondence and national platform, (2 folders)
      - National Committee, News Release and Straight from the Shoulder
      - National Committee, News Release, (2 folders)
      - Pamphlets (Box 4)
      - Eisenhower's nomination acceptance speech and printed material
      - Race relations
      - Clippings
  - 1960:
    - AFL-CIO, Committee on Political Education (COPE)
    - Democratic Party
      - Advertising material
      - Bumper sticker
      - Clippings
      - Democratic Fact Sheet
      - Printed material
      - Religious issues
      - Young Democratic Clubs
    - Non-partisan, factual campaign information, party platforms, (2 folders)
    - Republican Party (Box 5)
      - Clippings
      - Major speeches before the National Convention
      - Printed material
      - Publicity materials
      - Speeches
  - 1964:
    - Democratic Party
      - Pamphlets, AFL-CIO endorsement and other printed material
      - Scientists, Engineers and Physicians for Johnson and Humphrey, (2 folders)
    - Non-partisan
      - Biography of Lyndon Baines Johnson and The National Voter, "Candidates of 1964"
      - Time, "Election Extra," Nov. 4
    - Republican Party, campaign fundraisers and printed material
    - Rightist organizations, printed material
  - 1966: (Box 6)
    - Republican Party, campaign fundraising
  - 1968:
    - AFL-CIO, printed material
    - American Independent Party, printed material
    - Democratic Party
      - Duke Committee for Humphrey-Muskie
      - McCarthy, Eugene
      - Printed material
    - Republican Party, printed material, Rockefeller, Nelson
  - 1970:
    - Democratic Party, campaign fundraising
  - 1971:
    - People's Coalition for Peace and Justice
  - 1972:
    - Democratic Party, printed material
    - Republican Party Partner in Progress and other printed material
  - 1973:
    - Democratic Party, History of Democratic Women and other printed material
    - Republican Party, sustaining member card
  - 1976:
    - Democratic Party
      - Candidates
      - Printed material
    - Libertarian Party, return envelope, MacBride
    - Republican Party
      - National Convention registration
      - Printed material
  - 1978:
    - Republican Party, Congressional elections promotion by Gerald Ford
  - 1980:
    - Citizens Party, Commoner, Barry
    - Democratic Party, printed material
    - Independents, Anderson, John
    - Republican Party, printed material
  - 1982:
    - Independent
      - Americans for Common Sense, McGovern, George
      - People for the American Way, Lear, Norman
    - Republican Party, economic program and other printed material
  - 1983-1985:
    - Libertarian Party, convention and other printed material
  - 1984:
    - Democratic Party, presidential and congressional elections, fundraising letters, and other printed material
    - Independent, Independents for Mondale-Ferraro
    - Republican Party
      - Printed material
      - Senate Journal and reelection poll
  - 1996:
    - Democratic Party
      - Bumper sticker
      - Stickers
  - 2000:
    - Democratic Party
      - Bumper stickers, Gore, Al
  - 2008:
    - Democratic Party
      - Printed material and presidential inauguration tickets for ceremony and parade (2009), Obama, Barack
    - Republican Party
      - Printed material
  - Undated:
    - Democratic Party(?), American presidents dress tie
    - Republican Party, bumper sticker and sticker
- "America Votes" Series, 1850-1984, (2 boxes)
  A variety of materials from a 1996 exhibit at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library on U.S. political campaigns.
  - 1850s: (Box 6)
    - Know-Nothing Platform
  - 1888:
    - Cleveland, Grover
  - 1904 or 1912:
    - Roosevelt, Theodore
  - 1930s-1940s:
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
  - 1952-1956:
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D.
    - Stevenson, Adlai
  - 1952:
    - Greenback Party
    - Pogo
  - 1960: (Box 7)
    - Kennedy, John F.
  - 1960, 1968-1972:
    - Nixon, Richard
  - 1964:
    - Johnson, Lyndon Baines
    - Goldwater, Barry
  - 1968:
    - Humphrey, Hubert
  - 1976-1980:
    - Carter, Jimmy
  - 1976:
    - Ford, Gerald
    - Libertarian Party
    - Sanford, Terry
  - 1980:
    - Anderson, John
  - 1984:
    - Mondale, Walter
    - Reagan, Ronald
- State Elections Series, 1936-2008 and undated, (3 boxes)
  - 1936: (Box 7)
    - North Carolina, Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign
  - 1940:
    - North Carolina, Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign, Broughton, J. M.
  - 1948:
    - North Carolina, Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign, Scott, W. Kerr
  - 1950:
    - North Carolina, U.S. Senate campaign, Smith, Willis
  - 1952:
    - Louisiana, Republican and Non-partisan
    - North Carolina
      - Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign, Olive, Hubert E.
      - Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign, Umstead, William Bradley, (4 folders)
      - Democratic Primary, May 31
      - Democratic and Republican parties
      - Democratic Party, Congressional campaign, Tally, Joe O.
    - Wisconsin, Democratic Party, U.S. Senate campaign, Reuss, Henry
  - 1960:
    - North Carolina
      - Democratic Party
        - Congressional campaign, Kornegay, Horace
        - Gubernatorial campaign, Lake, Isaac Beverly
        - Gubernatorial campaign, Sanford, Terry
        - Gubernatorial campaign, Seawall Jr., Malcom Buie
        - Senatorial campaign, Jordan, B. Everett
        - State legislative and local campaigns
      - Republican Party
        - Congressional campaigns
        - Gubernatorial campaign, Gavin, Bob
        - State Legislature and local campaigns
  - 1962:
    - Kansas, Dole, Bob
  - 1962:
    - North Carolina, State elections
  - 1964:
    - New York, Democratic Party, U.S. Senate campaignKennedy, Robert
  - 1964: (Box 8)
    - North Carolina
      - Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign, Lake, Beverly
      - Democratic Party, State Elections
      - Republican Party, gubernatorial campaign, Preyer, Richard
      - Republican Party, State Elections
  - 1964:
    - Wyoming, Democratic Party, Historians for Senator McGee
  - 1966:
    - North Carolina
      - Democratic Party, Congressional campaigns, 5th District
      - Republican Party, Congressional campaign, Gardner, Jim
  - 1968:
    - North Carolina
      - Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign, Scott, Bob
      - Local election material, Durham
      - State Elections
  - 1972:
    - North Carolina
      - Democratic Party, gubernatorial campaign, Bowles, Hargrove Skipper
      - Republican Party, gubernatorial campaign, Holshouser, Jim
      - Local campaigns, Durham
      - U.S. Senate campaign, Helms, Jesse
      - State Elections
  - 1972-1974:
    - North Carolina, State Elections
  - 1973, 1982:
    - North Carolina, Congressman Ike Andrews
  - 1974:
    - North Carolina, State Elections
  - 1976:
    - Maryland, U.S. Senate campaigns
  - 1976:
    - North Carolina, State Elections
  - 1976-1984:
    - North Carolina, Durham Voters Alliance
  - 1977:
    - North Carolina
      - Report of the Resolutions Committee, Durham County Democratic Convention
      - Democratic Party, U.S. Senate campaign, Smith, McNeill
  - 1977-1978:
    - North Carolina, State Elections
  - 1979-1984:
    - North Carolina, State Elections
  - 1981: (Box 9)
    - Massachusetts, Democratic Party, U.S. Senate campaign, Kennedy, Ted
  - 1981-1982:
    - North Carolina, State Elections
  - 1982:
    - North Carolina
      - Washington Update, Senator John East
      - State elections
  - 1984:
    - Minnesota, Democratic Party U.S. Senate campaign, Growe, Joan
  - 1984:
    - North Carolina
      - Republican Party, gubernatorial campaign, Martin, Jim
      - State elections, (2 folders)
  - 1985:
    - North Carolina, Washington Update, Valentine, Tim, and CBS stock buyout plan to end liberal bias, Helms, Jesse
  - 1996:
    - North Carolina
      - Durham County Commissioner elections
      - State elections
  - 2008:
    - North Carolina
      - Durham ballot and early voting materials for Barack Obama, Democratic ticket printed materials
      - State judges
      - Governor and U.S. Senate
  - Undated:
    - American Communist Workers Movement and other printed material
- Political Campaign Memorabilia Series, 1908-2000 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Consists primarily of campaign buttons.
  - 1908: (Box 10)
    - Taft, William
  - 1924-1928:
    - Coolidge, Calvin
  - 1932 and undated:
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
  - 1948:
    - Truman, Harry
    - Dewey, Thomas
  - 1952:
    - Harriman, William Averell
    - Kefauver, Estes
    - Kerr, Robert
    - Russell, Richard B.
  - 1952-1956:
    - Eisenhower, Dwight
    - Stevenson, Adlai
  - 1956:
    - Kefauver, Estes
  - 1960:
    - Kennedy, John F., (matchbox)
    - Nixon, Richard
  - 1964:
    - Johnson, Lyndon B.
  - 1968:
    - Humphrey, Hubert
    - Rockefeller, Nelson
    - Wallace, George
  - 1972:
    - McGovern, George
    - Sanford, Terry
  - 1974:
    - Humor, I Like Buttons
  - 1976:
    - Carter, Jimmy
  - 1981:
    - Anti-Reagan
  - 1984:
    - Reagan, Ronald
    - Mondale, Walter
  - 1988:
    - Anti-Bush
  - 1996: (Box 11)
    - Clinton, Bill
  - 2000:
    - Gore, Al
  - Undated, Miscellaneous Democratic Party
  - Maryland:
    - 1938, Tydings, Millard
    - 1970, Tydings, Joe
    - 1976, Sarbanes, Nick
    - circa 1976, Beall (Jr?), James Glenn
  - North Carolina:
    - 1968, Galifianakis, Nick
    - 1980, Hunt, Jim
    - 1996, Gant, Harvey
    - Undated:
      - Campbell, Ralph
      - Hunt, Jim
      - Scott, Bob
- Oversize Material, 1948-1984, (1 box and 2 oversize folders)
  - 1948: (Box 12)
    - Republican Party, clippings
  - 1952:
    - Democratic Party, The Democrat and other clippings
    - Republican Party, campaign materials and clippings
  - 1956:
    - Independent, Byrd, Harry
    - Republican Party, clippings
  - 1960:
    - AFL-CIO, C.O.P.E., voter registration posters
    - Democratic Party, bumper sticker, clippings and posters
    - Non-partisan, clippings
    - Republican Party, convention hat and poster of ephemera
  - 1968:
    - Republican Party, Rockefeller, Nelson
  - 1971:
    - Black and white photographic mask of Vietnam era U.S. military officer
    - Newspapers
      - New Solidarity
      - News of Greece
      - Spring Movement
      - Workers' Power
  - 1972:
    - Democratic Party, clipping
  - 1976:
    - Penthouse election coverage advertisement
  - 1984:
    - Independent, sign, Mondale, Walter
  - 1952:
    - Wisconsin, Democratic Party, U.S. Senate campaign, Reuss, Henry clippings
  - 1960:
    - North Carolina, Precinct map, city of Durham
  - 1960
    - Rockefeller, Nelson (Opaperfolder 1)
  - 1963:
    - North Carolina, Durham Committe on Negro Affairs, election poster (Box 12)
  - 1964:
    - North Carolina, Republican Party, Gubernatorial campaign, Preyer, Richard, People for Preyer, newspaper
    - Democratic Party, Presidential campaign, Johnson, Lyndon B. (Opaperfolder 1)
  - 1968
    - Humphrey, Hubert (Opaperfolder 1)
  - 1973:
    - North Carolina, U.S. Senate campaign, Wilson, Henry Hall (Box 12)
  - 1976:
    - Maryland, U.S. Senate Race, Sarbanes, Paul
  - 1976, North Carolina:
    - Congressional campaign, Ramsey, Jim
    - Gubernatorial campaigns
      - Hunt, Jim
      - O'Herron, Ed
      - Wood, George
  - 1980, North Carolina, Democratic Party:
    - Gubernatorial campaign, Hunt, Jim
    - U.S. Senate campaign, Morgan, Robert
  - 1984
    - Mondale, Walter, and Geraldine Ferraro (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Reagan, Ronald (Opaperfolder 1)
  - 1984, North Carolina: (Box 12)
    - Democratic Party
      - Campaign Journal
      - State Auditor campaign, Renfrow, Ed
    - Non-partisan, North Carolina Independent
    - Republican Party, The Landmark
    - Attorney General campaign, Foster, Allen (Opaperfolder 1)